A Guide to the Organization cards of the Virginia Dept. of Military Affairs, 1876-1947
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Organization cards of the Virginia Dept. of Military Affairs, 1876-1947
The Library of Virginia
51986
23 reels of microfilm
Military Affairs, Virginia Dept. of
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Film duplicated and accessioned 10 April 2017.
Scope and Content
These cards provide information about Virginia soldiers in various military organizations, 1876-1947. The index cards are generally pre-printed with fields to include name, rank, company and regiment, and dates of service and various other types of information (specific information for each type of card provided below). The cards cover organizations that include Army, Navy, Marine Corps, Virginia Protective Force, Virginia Reserve Militia, and Virginia National Guard, both enlisted and officers. The majority of the cards document soldiers who participated in World War I, but there are a few series of cards that document World War II soldiers, and a few series of cards that document soldiers prior to WWI.
Cards are only available on microfilm (16 mm). Cards are in alphabetical order by surname of soldier within each type of cards, but cards were filmed in two rows. For each reel, records begin on the bottom row and run forwards in alphabetical order, and then are in reverse alphabetical order on the top row. Some cards may be dark and difficult to read.
These cards document the following:
Army (WWI) - Enlisted, 1917-1919. These cards include name, serial number, race, residence, where inducted and date, place and date of birth, organizations served in with dates of assignment and transfers, grades (rank) with date(s) of appointment, engagements, Wounded in Action/injuries received in action (degree of injury and date), served overseas with dates, honorably discharged on demobilization with date, percent disabled in view of occupation, and remarks. May also include information on decorations and citations. Cards are separated by race (White or African-American).
Army (WWI) - Officers, 1917-1919. These cards include name, race, residence, where born, appointed from and date, attended, promotions, organizations and staff assignments, principal stations, engagements, wounds received, served overseas and dates, honorable discharge and date, percent disabled in view of occupation, and remarks. Cards are separated by race (White or African-American). May also include Applications for Victory Medal, which include name, rank and organization, major operations participated in, defensive sector service, service abroad, applicant signature, address and approving officer signature.
Army Deaths (WWI) - Enlisted, 1917-1919. These cards include name, serial number, race, residence, place of birth, date of birth or age, organizations served in with dates of assignment and transfers, grade (rank) with date of appointment, engagement, killed in action and date, wounds or other injuries received in action, served overseas with dates, death date and cause of death, name of person notified of the death and relationship to the deceased, and remarks. Cards are separated by race (White or African-American).
Army Deaths (WWI) - Officers, 1917-1919. Cards include name, race, residence, inducted at and date, place and date of birth, organizations served in with dates and assignments and transfers, grade (rank) with date of appointment, engagements, wounds or other injuries received in action, and remarks.
Army Wounded (WWI) - Enlisted, 1917-1919. Cards include name, serial number, race, residence, where inducted and date, place of birth, date of birth or age, organizations served in with dates of assignment and transfers, grade (rank) with date of appointment, engagements, wounded in action/injuries received in service (degree of injury and date), served overseas with date, honorable discharged on demobilization date, percent disabled in view of occupation, and remarks. May also note any decoration or citations and whether applications for medals have been filed. Cards are separated by race (White or African-American).
Army Wounded (WWI) - Officers, 1917-1919. Cards include name, race, where born and age, where appointed and date, rank, promotions, organizations, assignments, principal stations, served overseas and date, wounded in action (place, date, extent) and remarks. Remarks may include overflow from other fields. May also include Applications for Victory Medal, which include name, rank and organization, major operations participated in, defensive sector service, service abroad, applicant signature, address and approving officer signature.
Marine Corps
Mexican Border, 1916-1917. Cards include name, rank, company and regiment, date commissioned or enlisted, and date discharged. May also note if mustered out to federal service and date. Cards for enlisted soldiers and officers are filed together.
Navy (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers, 1917-1919. Cards include name, serial number, where enlisted and date, age at entrance, rate (rank), home address, served at and dates, served as (rank) and number of days, date of discharge, place and rating at discharge, and remarks. Cards of enlisted men and officers, and white and African-American soldiers are interfiled.
Navy Deaths (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers, 1917-1919. Cards include name, serial number, where enlisted and date, age at entrance, rate (rank), home address, served at and dates, served as (rank) and number of days, date and place where died, rating at death, and remarks. Cards of enlisted men and officers, and white and African-American soldiers are interfiled.
Naval Reserves (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers, 1917-1919. Cards of enlisted men and officers, and white and African-American soldiers are interfiled. Cards for enlisted and officers are slightly different. Cards for enlisted soldiers include name, rank, date and place of birth, appointed from, record of service, appointments, inactive duty, and resignation/disenrollment/discharge. Cards for officers include name, date and place of birth, appointed from, home address, date of appointment, rank on appointment, promotions, duty assignments, and final disposition.
German War (WWI), 1916-1917. Cards include name, rank, date enlisted, and date discharged. Also include a reference to muster roll book and page number.
Spanish American War, 1898-1899. Cards include name, rank, company and regiment, date enlisted, date mustered into federal service, and date discharged.
Virginia National Guard (WWII), 1941-1942. Cards include name, inducted and revert to state control date, National Guard unit in federal service, date enlisted in National Guard and number of years, attached to state department, date transferred, and date discharged. May also note if recalled to active duty, released from federal service, reverted to state control or detailed to active duty.
Virginia National Guard Locator Cards, 1919-1941. Cards include name, company and regiment, enlisted date (may include duration on of enlistment), and may include discharged or transferred dates.
Virginia Volunteers, 1884-1917. Cards include name, company and regiment, date enlisted, and date discharged. May also note if called into federal service and if company was disbanded with date and general order number.
Virginia Volunteers - African-American troops, 1876-1897. Cards include name, company and regiment, date enlisted, date mustered into federal service, and discharge date.
Volunteers for Emergencies (WWI), 1917-1920. Cards include name, rank, company, date enlisted, and date discharged. May also not if company was disbanded with date and general order number.
Contents List
- Organization cards of the Virginia Dept. of Military Affairs,, 1876-1947., Extent: 23 reels of microfilm. (Reel 6320-6342)
  - Virginia Reserve Militia Minute Men - Officers (A-Z), 1942-1945. (Reel 6320)
  - Virginia Reserve Militia Minute Men - Enlisted (A-S), 1942-1945. (Reel 6320)
  - Virginia Reserve Militia Minute Men - Enlisted (T-Z), 1942-1945. (Reel 6321)
  - Virginia Protective Forces/Virginia State Guard (A-Mif), 1941-1947. (Reel 6321)
  - Virginia Protective Forces/Virginia State Guard (Mil-Z), 1941-1947. (Reel 6322)
  - Army Deaths (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6322)
  - Army Deaths (WWI) - Enlisted (African-American) (A-Y), 1917-1919. (Reel 6322)
  - Army Wounded (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (A-Ca), 1917-1919. (Reel 6322)
  - Army Wounded (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (Ce-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6323)
  - Army Wounded (WWI) - Enlisted (African-American) (A-Y), 1917-1919. (Reel 6323)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (Bu-Fri), 1917-1919. (Reel 6324)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (Fro-Le), 1917-1919. (Reel 6325)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (Li-Ross), 1917-1919. (Reel 6326)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (Rossano-Wilson, H.), 1917-1919. (Reel 6327)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (white) (Wilson, J.-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6328)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (African-American) (A-Gol), 1917-1919. (Reel 6328)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (African-American) (Goo-Randall, J.), 1917-1919. (Reel 6329)
  - Army (WWI) - Enlisted (African-American) (Randall, M.-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Marine Corps Deaths (WWI) - Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Marine Corps Deaths (WWI) - Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Marine Corps (WWI) - Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Marine Corps (WWI) - Enlisted (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Army Deaths (WWI) - Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Army Wounded (WWI) - Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Army (WWI) - Officers (white) (A-Bo), 1917-1919. (Reel 6330)
  - Army (WWI) - Officers (white) (Br-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6331)
  - Army (WWI) - Officers (African-American) (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6331)
  - Navy (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers (A-Cop), 1917-1919. (Reel 6331)
  - Navy (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers (Cor-Sha), 1917-1919. (Reel 6332)
  - Navy (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers (She-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6333)
  - Navy Deaths (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6333)
  - Naval Reserves (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6333)
  - Naval Reserves Deaths (WWI) - Enlisted and Officers (A-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6333)
  - German War (A-He), 1917-1919. (Reel 6333)
  - German War (Hi-Z), 1917-1919. (Reel 6334)
  - Volunteers for Emergencies, 1917-1920. (Reel 6334)
  - Locator Cards - Enlisted (A-Atk), 1919-1941. (Reel 6334)
  - Locator Cards - Enlisted (Atl-Flou), 1919-1941. (Reel 6335)
  - Locator Cards - Enlisted (Flow-Livesay, Lee), 1919-1941. (Reel 6336)
  - Locator Cards - Enlisted (Livesay, Leroy-Snyder, J.), 1919-1941. (Reel 6337)
  - Locator Cards - Enlisted (Snyder, L.-Z), 1919-1941. (Reel 6338)
  - Virginia National Guard Inducted and Reverted to State Control, 1941-1942. (Reel 6338)
  - Virginia Volunteers (A-Brockenbrough, E.), 1884-1917. (Reel 6338)
  - Virginia Volunteers (Brockenbrough, J.-Loh), 1884-1917. (Reel 6339)
  - Virginia Volunteers (Lom-Turner, F.A.), 1884-1917. (Reel 6340)
  - Virginia Volunteers (Turner, F.V.-Z), 1884-1917. (Reel 6341)
  - Spanish American War, 1898-1899. (Reel 6341)
  - Virginia Volunteers (African-American), 1876-1897. (Reel 6341)
  - Mexican Border (A-Ha), 1914-1917. (Reel 6341)
  - Mexican Border (He-Z), 1914-1917. (Reel 6342)